DMITRY GUTOV

SENIOR BACKEND DEVELOPER

CONTACT

dmitry@gutov.dev



Cyprus, Limassol

http://github.com/dgutov

https://t.me/dgutov

https://www.linkedin.com/in/dgutov/

+35797736876

SKILLS

Ruby, Rails **JavaScript**

Go

Elixir

Java

MySQL

PostgresQL

Redis

InfluxDB

OpenStack

TDD

dry-rb

REST

EDUCATION

M.S.

Saint-Petersburg State University

2003-2009

Mathematics & Mechanics Faculty, Mechanics and Applied Mathematics

LANGUAGES

English (C2)

Russian (Native)

Greek (B1)

PROFILE

I'm a sofware development professional with 10+ years of experience with Ruby on Rails (and other frameworks) and a proven track record in architecting, optimizing, and maintaining significant software projects over the years. Working with stakeholders to derive precise requirements, doing research and collaborating with the team to create optimal solutions. Scaling the systems vertically, horizontally and geographically too.

I enjoy complex challenges and open-ended problems, and I care about the user's experience (whether that is the external customer, or an internal team consuming an API).

In my spare time I work on open-source software (mostly Lisp, but also Ruby and a little C).

WORK HISTORY

Senior Software Developer

2013-2023

Servers.com

Pivotal role in developing the cloud platform backend. Building the internal applications from the ground up (those that operate OpenStack clusters and a PowerDNS installation), driving the architecture, collaborating with the sysadmin team, doing code reviews, ensuring good test coverage, setting up generation of API documentation, debugging performance problems and memory leaks, doing assorted feature work on a number of apps, internal- and external-facing.

Common Tech: Ruby, RSpec, Grape, ActiveRecord, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, Sidekig, InfluxDB, Puma, Faraday, Sentry, Elastic APM, Swagger UI, Gitlab, JIRA.

Cloud Platform

- Integration with OpenStack installations (Identity/Storage/Compute/Network/Image/...), HTTP Ruby clients for them.
- Virtual server configuration build-up and associated provisioning for network hardware.
- Health checking subsystem (for backend apps and on-premise services) for automated monitoring.
- UCDN integration.
- Metering resource usage (with different algorithms for different resources), historical accounting and summaries for invoicing.
- Bulk importing customer files from third-party storages (such as S3).

Extra Tech: OpenStack, EventMachine, em-synchrony, Extreme SLX-OS REST API.

DNSaaS

Written the service up and oversaw its futher development.

- · Web API that interacts with the PowerDNS database.
- · Distributed healthchecking and customer notifications (first for domain records, and later for customer servers).

Extra Tech: PowerDNS, microservices.

Customer Control Panel and CRM

- · Baremetal server provisioning.
- Integration with internal services (such as Cloud Computing, DNS, etc).
- · Mass-mail subsystem with flexible filtering and custom DSL for messages that autogenerates text (and markup) enumerating customer-owner resources.
- Geographically distributed computations.
- Migration of baremetal servers and their configurations from a different data center, driven by a different ERP system.
- Deployment scripts for test (sandbox) installations with chat bot interface.
- Feature development, code review, refactoring.

Extra Tech: dry-rb, Sinatra, Sequel, rspec_api_documentation, Ansible, PXE.

2011-2012

Full-Stack Developer Carbonfay

https://carbonfay.ru/

Brief Busters

Single-page application for creating and filling [design] brief templates.

Tech: Backbone.js, Rails, Thinking Sphinx.

Role: The sole developer, full-stack.

Roborealty

Real estate advertisements aggregator.

Provided sections for companies and agents, advanced search, map view, photo duplicates detection, automated rating calculation, "smart" pros/cons descriptions, lot owner interface, and promotion mechanics. The Database was seeded and kept up to date with a number of specialized parsers that walk advertisement boards and agency websites on a fixed schedule.

Tech: Ruby, Rails, ¡Query, Google Maps, pHash.

Role: Designed the system and wrote ~80% of the code, from backend to frontend.

Software Developer (Java)

2010-2011

Actimind

https://www.actimind.com

ActiTIME

https://www.actitime.com/

Web-based timesheet tracking and reporting application.

Tech: Java 1.4, Struts 1.3, JDBC, Ext JS, JSON-RPC-Java, MockCreator.

- · Developed reusable interface components.
- Separated advanced features to make targeted editions. General maintenance.

Scam Investigator

Custom multi-tiered system designed to search, identify, and collect required data about scammy web merchants, while crawling the web.

The codebase is comprised of two Mozilla Firefox extensions (operator interface and bot driver) and a central node which coordinates and schedules tasks.

Tech: Java 1.5, Mozilla LiveConnect, Struts 2, JPA, Ext JS, Mockito.

- Refactored the engine code to merge the tracking and collection phases.
- Implemented a new source type and related infrastructure to initiate crawlings from search engine queries. General maintenance.

Software Developer (Java) CJSC LMA

2008-2010

https://www.labma.ru/

Digital Catalogue for the Address Information Department

Geographically distributed system designed to transfer, process and display the registry data from the Federal Migration Service database.

Tech: Java 6, ICEfaces, EJB3, SOAP.

- Developed front ends for the first user-facing modules. Redesigned the schema for the addresses database.
- Implemented Criteria-like API on top of JPA 1.0.
- General development and maintenance.

Infoportal LETI

Intranet application for lecturers and students used to manage courses, grades, schedules, reading materials, faculty personnel data, etc.

Tech: Java CAPS, Ext-GWT, JDBC.

Role: Designed and implemented about half of the sections, from the database schema to the services and the user interface.